Guide to the Dick Thornburgh Papers, 1932- AIS.1998.30.13
ULS Archives & Special Collections
- Attorney General of the United States, 1988-1991; XIII.
  - Transcripts, 3.
    - Hearing of the Senate Judiciary Committee regarding Justice Department budget, April 3, 1990 (Box 752, Folder 85)
    - Foreign Press Center briefing regarding trip to Ixtapa, Mexico, April 17, 1990 (Box 752, Folder 86)
    - CNN "Newsmaker Saturday" regarding crime in the USA, April 28, 1990 (Box 752, Folder 87)
    - Hearing of the House Judiciary Committee regarding Reauthorization for Fiscal Year 1991, May 16, 1990 (Box 752, Folder 88)
    - ABC "This Week with David Brinkley" regarding the Civil Rights Bill and Ayer's resignation, May 20, 1990 (Box 752, Folder 89)
    - Press conference at the FBI regarding proposed changes in the President's Crime Package, May 23, 1990 (Box 752, Folder 90)
    - CBS "Face the Nation" regarding savings and loans and civil rights, June 24, 1990 (Box 752, Folder 91)
    - Press availability with Business Higher Education Council leaders regarding minorities, June 25, 1990 (Box 752, Folder 92)
    - Speech to the Heritage Foundation regarding "The Soviet Union and the Rule of Law" (including questions and answers), July 10, 1990 (Box 752, Folder 93)
    - Press conference with Marvin Collins regarding indictment of Edwin T. McBirney III of Sunbelt Savings Associations, July 11, 1990 (Box 752, Folder 94)
    - NBC "Today Show" regarding savings and loans, July 12, 1990 (Box 752, Folder 95)
    - ABC "This Week with David Brinkley" regarding Neil Bush and the "Super Scandal: The Savings and Loans Bailout", July 15, 1990 (Box 752, Folder 96)
    - News conference with John Sununu regarding the Civil Rights Bill of 1990, July 17, 1990 (Box 752, Folder 97)
    - CBS "This Morning" regarding Civil Rights Bill of 1990, July 20, 1990 (Box 752, Folder 98)
    - ABC "Nightline" regarding David Souter's Supreme Court nomination, July 23, 1990 (Box 752, Folder 99)
    - ABC "Good Morning America" regarding David Souter's Supreme Court nomination, July 24, 1990 (Box 752, Folder 100)
    - CNN Interview regarding savings and loans and David Souter's Supreme Court nomination, July 24, 1990 (Box 752, Folder 101)
    - Hearing of the Senate Judiciary Committee regarding banking fraud, July 24, 1990 (Box 752, Folder 102)
    - National Press Club Address: "Box Score on the Savings and Loans" (including questions and answers), July 25, 1990 (Box 752, Folder 103)
    - Excerpts from remarks following signing of Americans with Disabilities Act (ADA), July 26, 1990 (Box 752, Folder 104)
    - Address at the Annual Meeting of the American Legislative Exchange Council regarding civil rights, crime, drugs, firearms, and David Souter's Supreme Court nomination, July 27, 1990 (Box 752, Folder 105)
    - Hearing of the Senate Banking Committee regarding bank and thrift fraud, August 2, 1990 (Box 752, Folder 106)
    - John McLaughlin's "One on One" regarding Iraq and Kuwait, August 3, 1990 (Box 752, Folder 107)
    - ABC Interview with Walt Rogers regarding Iraq and Kuwait, Henry Barr, Gray leak, and violent crime, August 8, 1990 (Box 752, Folder 108)
    - U.S./ Mexico Binational Commissions press conference with Secretary Brady regarding the Drug Enforcement Administration (DEA) and Dr. Alvarez Machain, August 8, 1990 (Box 752, Folder 109)
    - Remarks by the AG and Soviet Minister of Justice Veniamin Yakovlev during Opening Plenary Session of Justice Conference, August 13, 1990 (Box 752, Folder 110)
    - AG and Soviet Minister of Justice Veniamin Yakovlev regarding the Rule of Law and subjects of mutual interest, August 13, 1990 (Box 752, Folder 111)
    - Remarks at Robert Bonner's swearing-in ceremony as Administrator of DEA, August 16, 1990 (Box 752, Folder 112)
    - Joint American and Russian Conference with Soviet Minister of Justice Veniamin F. Yakovlev, August 17, 1990 (Box 752, Folder 113)
    - C-Span Call-In Interview regarding civil rights, David Souter's Supreme Court nomination, savings and loans crisis, Henry Barr, Noriega, gun control, drugs, Nazi war criminals, and white collar crime, August 22, 1990 (Box 752, Folder 114)
    - White House statement regarding the Crime Bill, September 12, 1990 (Box 753, Folder 1)
    - Symposium regarding The Role of the Attorney General, September 17, 1990 (Box 753, Folder 2)
    - Address to the Voice of America Drug Workshop (including questions and answers), September 24, 1990 (Box 753, Folder 3)
    - Press Conference regarding Crime Bill, September 26, 1990 (Box 753, Folder 4)
    - Remarks to the Redress Payments ceremony for Japanese American Internment victims, October 9, 1990 (Box 753, Folder 5)
    - CNN "The World Today" regarding Civil Rights Act, October 22, 1990 (Box 753, Folder 6)
    - Press Conference regarding the Indictment against Jarrett E. Woods, Jr of Western Savings Association, October 25, 1990 (Box 753, Folder 7)
    - Opening remarks at the Financial Institution Fraud Enforcement Conference, November 6, 1990 (Box 753, Folder 8)
    - Remarks at the Combined Federal Campaign kickoff, November 6, 1990 (Box 753, Folder 9)
    - Press Conference regarding Indictment in Mail Bomb Murders, November 7, 1990 (Box 753, Folder 10)
    - Memorial services for FBI special agents, November 14, 1990 (Box 753, Folder 11)
    - Symposium regarding the 25th Anniversary of the Voting Rights Act, November 16, 1990 (Box 753, Folder 12)
    - Press conference regarding signing a Mutual Legal Assistance Treaty with Spain, November 20, 1990 (Box 753, Folder 13)
    - White House briefing regarding meeting with Mexican officials, November 27, 1990 (Box 753, Folder 14)
    - Law Enforcement Training Network (LETN) Question and Answer and interview, February 7, 1991 (Box 753, Folder 15)
    - Press Conference regarding Banca Nazionale del Lavoro (BNL), February 28, 1991 (Box 753, Folder 16)
    - ABC "Good Morning America" regarding violent crime, March 4, 1991 (Box 753, Folder 17)
    - Closing remarks at the 1991 Crime Summit, March 5, 1991 (Box 753, Folder 18)
    - "MacNeil/Lehrer News Hour" regarding crime, March 11, 1991 (Box 753, Folder 19)
    - Press Conference regarding settlement of Exxon Alaskan Oil Spill Case, March 13, 1991 (Box 753, Folder 20)
    - NBC "Meet the Press" regarding crime, punishment and police brutality, March 17, 1991 (Box 753, Folder 21)
    - CBS, "This Morning" regarding the civil rights bill, crime bill, and gun control, April 4, 1991 (Box 753, Folder 22)
    - CNN "Newsmaker Sunday" regarding "The President's Crime Bill: Does It Go Far Enough?", April 7, 1991 (Box 753, Folder 23)
    - ABC "Good Morning America" regarding the crime bill and gun control, April 10, 1991 (Box 753, Folder 24)
    - Hearing of the Senate Judiciary Committee regarding "Crime Control: The Administration's View", April 18, 1991 (Box 753, Folder 25)
    - CNN "Crier & Co." regarding Victims Crime Week, April 19, 1991 (Box 753, Folder 26)
    - CBS "This Morning," and ABC regarding Victims Crime Week, April 21, 1991 (Box 753, Folder 27)
    - CBS "This Morning" regarding Victims Crime Week and the Brady Bill, April 22, 1991 (Box 753, Folder 28)
    - Address by President Bush and the Attorney General at the signing ceremony for National Crime Victims Rights Week, April 22, 1991 (Box 753, Folder 29)
    - U.S. Conference of Mayors, Fifth Annual Meeting on Crime and Drugs regarding "Cracking Down on Violent Crime" (including questions and answers), April 23, 1991 (Box 753, Folder 30)
    - NPR "All Things Considered" regarding Supreme Court Victim Impact Statements, April 24, 1991 (Box 753, Folder 31)
    - CBS "Evening News" regarding Supreme Court Victim Impact Statements, April 24, 1991 (Box 753, Folder 32)
    - ABC WJLA-TV, Channel 7 regarding Victim Impact Statements, April 24, 1991 (Box 753, Folder 33)
    - Proceedings of Supreme Court Case: Payne v. Tennessee, April 24, 1991 (Box 753, Folder 34)
    - Fox WTTG-TV, Channel 5 regarding Victim Impact Statements, April 24, 1991 (Box 753, Folder 35)
    - ABC "Good Morning America" regarding Victim Impact Statements, April 25, 1991 (Box 753, Folder 36)
    - ABC "World News This Morning" regarding Victim Impact Statements, April 25, 1991 (Box 753, Folder 37)
    - CBS "Eyewitness News" regarding Legal Advocates in Education, April 26, 1991 (Box 753, Folder 38)
    - Address to Annual Judicial Conference, Chicago, April 29, 1991 (Box 753, Folder 39)
    - ABC, Interview with Tim O'Brien regarding Miranda, May 1991 (Box 753, Folder 40)
    - Press Conference regarding Antitrust College Investigation, May 22, 1991 (Box 753, Folder 41)
    - ABC "This Week with David Brinkley" regarding Civil Rights Bill, June 2, 1991 (Box 753, Folder 42)
    - Remarks by President Bush regarding Thornburgh's plans to become a candidate for Senate, June 4, 1991 (Box 753, Folder 43)
    - ABC Interview with Tim O'Brien regarding the Miranda rule, June 12, 1991 (Box 753, Folder 44)
    - Fox "Morning News" regarding the Crime Bill, June 13, 1991 (Box 753, Folder 45)
    - McNeil/Lehrer "News Hour" with Senator Biden regarding the Crime Bill, June 13, 1991 (Box 753, Folder 46)
    - ABC "This Week with David Brinkley" regarding the Supreme Court after Marshall, June 30, 1991 (Box 753, Folder 47)
    - NBC "Meet the Press" regarding the Supreme Court, June 30, 1991 (Box 753, Folder 48)
    - ABC "Good Morning America" regarding Clarence Thomas' Nomination to the Supreme Court, July 2, 1991 (Box 753, Folder 49)
    - NPR Interview with Claudil Sanchez regarding the Americans with Disabilities Act (ADA), July 23, 1991 (Box 753, Folder 50)
    - CBS "Face the Nation" regarding BCCI, August 4, 1991 (Box 753, Folder 51)
    - Press Conference regarding Weed and Seed (new anti-drug initiative), August 7, 1991 (Box 753, Folder 52)
    - Remarks of President Bush to the Fraternal Order of Police regarding Thornburgh's achievements for law enforcement, August 14, 1991 (Box 753, Folder 53)
    - Farewell Ceremony honoring Attorney General Thornburgh, August 15, 1991 (Box 753, Folder 54)
    - CNN "Evans and Novak" regarding Attorney General Thornburgh running for Senate, August 17, 1991 (Box 753, Folder 55)
    - Meeting with Jack Torry, Pittsburgh Post Gazette Reporter, regarding responsibilities as Attorney General, undated (Box 753, Folder 56)
  - Nomination and Confirmation Files, 4.
    While serving as Director of the Institute of Politics, John F. Kennedy School of Government, Harvard University, Thornburgh received a telephone call from A. B. Culvahouse. Jr., counsel to President Reagan, indicating that Reagan was interested in nominating Thornburgh to succeed Edwin Meese as Attorney General of the United States. Thornburgh says in his autobiography that he was "hardly expecting Culvahouse's call" because Thornburgh's recommendation to the President had come from former assistant attorney general William Weld, who was in "disfavor" with the Reagan administration for criticizing Meese (Evidence, p.199). However, Thornburgh did think himself one of the "logical candidates" for his "law enforcement, political and management record, as well as [his] good relations with the president and vice president" (Evidence, 199).
    But the call did come, and after meeting with President Reagan on July 12, 1988, he received the President's formal request to serve as Attorney General. Over the next month Thornburgh found himself in a whirlwind schedule of meetings, hearings, Washington visits, all of which required the perusal of preparatory research binders provided by the Department of Justice, the completion of forms and questionnaires, and attention to the memoranda and correspondence regarding details of his nomination process.
    The largest section of material here concerns the Senate Judiciary Committee Hearing on August 5, 1988, during which Thornburgh was interviewed and questioned regarding his positions on issues and his management of problems while Governor of Pennsylvania. This hearing required extensive research, much of it regarding Department of Justice issues, policies and problems Thornburgh handled during his governorship, as well as background on the members of the committee. In addition to research, there is also correspondence, Thornburgh's annotated notes, mock hearing questions and transcripts of the session (available here online).
    The Attorney General nomination and confirmation files are organized into the following five sections: 1)Nomination of Thornburgh as United States Attorney General, July, 1988, including news releases from the White House, statements by President Reagan and Thornburgh, and a published declaration of Thornburgh's nomination in the Congressional Record; 2) Nominee questionnaires and forms, 1988, which include the White House personal data statement, a questionnaire from the Senate Judiciary Committee (with Thornburgh's personal notes and draft responses to questions), financial disclosure forms, and other documents; 3) Research binders prepared for Senate Judiciary Committee hearing on August 5, 1988, which include research on committee members and questions and answers given by previous nominees, and a Thornburgh-annotated and "clean" (un-annotated) copy of a research binder on all Department of Justice components and issues within the DOJ; 4) Senate Judiciary Committee Hearing preparation and transcripts, includes information on Pennsylvania issues while Thornburgh was governor, transcripts of the hearing, and follow-up material, including questions and answers, courtesy calls, personal notes, and news clippings; and 5) Confirmation and swearing-in of Thornburgh as United States Attorney General, August-September, 1988, including a published declaration of Thornburgh's confirmation in the Congressional Record, lists and plans for the swearing-in ceremony on September 12, 1988 and remarks made by President Reagan and Attorney General Thornburgh at the ceremony.
    - Nomination of Thornburgh as United States Attorney General, July, 1988
      - President Reagan's nomination of Thornburgh as Attorney General: White House news releases and statements by President Reagan and Thornburgh, July 12, 1988 (Box 754, Folder 1)
      - Congressional Record, vol. 134, no. 107, nomination received, Dick Thornburgh of Pennsylvania to be Attorney General, July 25, 1988 (Box 754, Folder 2)
    - Nominee Questionnaires and Forms, 1988
      - FBI Data form and Thornburgh notes, July, 1988 (Box 754, Folder 3)
      - White House Personal Data Statement: Thornburgh notes and drafts and final copy, 1988 (Box 754, Folder 4-5)
      - Senate Judiciary Committee questionnaire: Thornburgh notes and draft responses, 1988 (Box 754, Folder 6-8)
      - "Confirmation Process" memorandum regarding process of nomination, confirmation and appointment, 1988 (Box 754, Folder 9)
      - Arthur B. Culvahouse, Counsel to the President: memorandum for prospective appointees regarding conflicts of interest for presidential appointees, July, 1988 (Box 754, Folder 10)
      - Presidential Appointees Handbook: prepared by National Academy of Public Administration, undated (Box 754, Folder 11)
      - Personal financial disclosure form (SF 278): Thornburgh notes and drafts, July, 1988 (Box 754, Folder 12)
      - Personal financial disclosure form (SF 278): correspondence between Office of Government Ethics, Kirkpatrick and Lockhart and U.S. Senate Committee on the Judiciary, July-August, 1988 (Box 754, Folder 13)
      - Personal financial disclosure form (SF 278): signed but without Ethics Committee notations, July 25, 1988 (Box 754, Folder 14)
      - Personal financial disclosure form (SF 278): final copy with Ethics Committee notations, July-August, 1988 (Box 754, Folder 15)
    - Research Binders Prepared for Senate Judiciary Committee Hearing, August 5, 1988
      - Research on Senate Judiciary Committee members, including bios, transcripts, articles and opinions by members, August, 1988 (Box 754, Folder 16)
      - Binder prepared by the Department of Justice (DOJ) containing questions and answers from all DOJ components and background, with Thornburgh annotations, August, 1988 (Box 754, Folder 17)
      - Binder prepared by the Department of Justice (DOJ) containing questions and answers from all DOJ components and background, with Thornburgh annotations, August, 1988 (Box 755, Folder 1-2)
      - Binder prepared by the Department of Justice (DOJ) containing questions and answers from all DOJ components and background, unmarked copy, August, 1988 (Box 755, Folder 3-5)
    - Senate Judiciary Committee Hearing Preparation and Transcripts, August 5, 1988
      - Department of Justice, Office of Legislative Affairs memorandum regarding mock hearing questions, August 3, 1988 (Box 755, Folder 6)
      - Hearing background research and preparation on topics including drugs, deportation procedures, judicial appointment of minorities, handguns and other topics, July-August, 1988 (Box 755, Folder 7)
      - Hearing background research and preparation on abortion, 1981-1988 (Box 755, Folder 8)
      - Hearing background research and preparation on McNally decision on mail fraud, 1987-1988 (Box 755, Folder 9)
      - Hearing background research and preparation on Thornburgh's 1966 Campaign for U.S. Congress and news clippings (Box 755, Folder 10)
      - Hearing background research and preparation on Thornburgh's accomplishments as U.S. Attorney, 1969-1977 (Box 755, Folder 11)
      - Hearing background research and preparation on Proceedings of Thornburgh's confirmation hearing for Assistant Attorney General, Criminal Division, June 12, 1975 (Box 756, Folder 1)
      - Hearing background research and preparation on Criminal Division, 1976-1977 (Box 756, Folder 2)
      - Hearing background research and preparation on Supreme Court case, Abney v. United States, October, 1976 (Box 756, Folder 3)
      - Hearing background research and preparation on Pennsylvania issues during Thornburgh's term as governor, 1985-1986 (Box 756, Folder 4)
      - Negative correspondence to Senate Judiciary Committee regarding Thornburgh's appointment as Attorney General, July 20, 1988 (Box 756, Folder 5)
      - Positive correspondence to Senate Judiciary Committee regarding Thornburgh's appointment as Attorney General, July-August, 1988 (Box 756, Folder 6)
      - Thornburgh's interview with the Auditor General's Office following Senate Judiciary Committee hearing, August 3, 1988 (Box 756, Folder 7)
      - Thornburgh's Washington DC schedule and courtesy calls with senators, July 25-28, 1988 (Box 756, Folder 8)
      - Partial Senate Judiciary Committee hearing transcript, with corrections, August 5, 1988 (Box 756, Folder 9)
      - Senate Judiciary Committee hearing transcript, morning and afternoon sessions, with Thornburgh's annotations, August 5, 1988 (Box 756, Folder 10)
      - Senate Judiciary Committee follow-up questions after hearing and Thornburgh's answers and background material, July-September, 1988 (Box 756, Folder 11)
      - Thornburgh's personal notes regarding nomination, hearing and appointment, July-August, 1988 (Box 756, Folder 12)
      - News clippings regarding Thornburgh's nomination and confirmation as Attorney General of the United States, July-August, 1988 (Box 756, Folder 13)
      - News clippings regarding Thornburgh's nomination and confirmation as Attorney General of the United States, July-August, 1988 (Box 756, Folder 14)
    - Confirmation and Swearing-in of Thornburgh as United States Attorney General, August-September, 1988
      - Congressional Record, vol. 134, no. 120, part 2, Confirmation of Thornburgh as Attorney General, August 11, 1988 (Box 756, Folder 15)
      - Swearing-in ceremony: memoranda and notes, lists and plans, August 12, 1988 (Box 756, Folder 16)
      - Swearing-in ceremony: remarks by Thornburgh and President Reagan and draft of Thornburgh's speech with annotations, August 12, 1988 (Box 756, Folder 17)
      - Swearing-in ceremony: questions and answers following ceremony with Attorney General Thornburgh, August 12, 1988 (Box 756, Folder 18)
  - Attorney General Thornburgh's Files, 5.
    These Attorney General files were kept by the staff of the Office of Attorney General and consist of topics that were of particular interest or usefulness to Thornburgh, both in his role as Attorney General (justice-related) and in his personal life (non-justice related). These were kept separately and are similarly separate here. The justice-related files are not to be seen as representing department priorities necessarily, but more files of convenience to the Attorney General. Among those are issue files referred to as "Nuggets," which were files of particular relevancy and interest, and which Thornburgh kept close at hand for ready reference.
    What is interesting, despite the more personal nature of these files, is that the notable topics and challenges of Thornburgh's years as Attorney General are well represented here. For example, the Savings and Loan (S and L) fraud scandal is a topic which dominates the "Nuggets" files, as drugs and related issues do with the Department of Justice files. Other prominent issues are crime and civil rights. It is fair to say that these files will have particular interest to researchers.
    The Attorney General's non-justice related files are simply issues and events in which he had a more personal interest. Here, you find topics ranging, just for example, from baseball to personal events, to Pennsylvania matters, lists of trips taken by the Attorney General, and files regarding his official Governor portrait hanging in 1991.
    The Attorney General's files are arranged as follows: 1) Department of Justice files (justice-related), an alphabetical listing of issues, people, organizations, events and other materials specifically related to Thornburgh's work as Attorney General. Large grouping of files, such as "Cases and investigations," are arranged alphabetically within each category (for example, by name of person or organization); 2) Attorney General's files (non-justice related), an alphabetical listing of issues, people, organizations, events and topics that are not necessarily related to his position at the Department of Justice; 3) Newspaper and magazine articles written about Thornburgh and kept in chronological order; 4) "Nugget" files; and 5) Telephone logs and messages, from the Office of the Attorney General.
    - Department of Justice Files (Justice-related)
      - Abortion: general materials, May, 1991 (Box 757, Folder 1)
      - Abortion: "Will Roe v. Wade be overruled?", article by Paul Keidinger, ABA Journal, July 1, 1988 (Box 757, Folder 2)
      - Abortion: Webster v. Reproductive Health Services, Supreme Court case, Docket No. 88-605, February-July, 1989 (Box 757, Folder 3)
      - Abortion: Wichita abortion clinic litigation, May, 1991 (Box 757, Folder 4)
      - Advisory Commission on Intergovernmental Regulations (ACIR), March, 1988-May, 1989 (Box 757, Folder 5)
      - AIDS/HIV, 1988-1990 (Box 757, Folder 6)
      - Air Carriers Access Act, February, 1990 (Box 757, Folder 7)
      - Alabama Fair Campaign Practices Act, August, 1989 (Box 757, Folder 8)
      - Alien Terrorist Removal Act, June, 1991 (Box 757, Folder 9)
      - American Bar Association (ABA), March, 1989-February, 1991 (Box 757, Folder 10)
      - American Bar Foundation Fellows, February, 1989 (Box 757, Folder 11)
      - American Civil Liberties Union (ACLU), September, 1988 (Box 757, Folder 12)
      - American Indian Law Newsletter, November-December, 1989 (Box 757, Folder 13)
      - Antitrust: enforcement and investigations, 1989-1991 (Box 757, Folder 14)
      - Articles: related to Department of Justice (DOJ), June, 1988-April, 1991 (Box 757, Folder 15)